A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Africa and Middle East Programs (AME), Program Staff Files FA503
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Africa and Middle East Programs (AME), Program Staff Files
1965-1976, 1987-1994
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA503
1.71 Cubic Feet 4 letter document boxes, 1 half-letter document box.
The Africa and Middle East (AME) Program originated in 1958 as the Near East and Africa Program, a regional program area within Overseas Development. It became part of the International Division in 1966 when the Overseas Development Program, along with other international Foundation programs became part of one International Division. A subsequent restructuring of the International Division occurred in 1980-1981 and led to the creation of the Developing Countries Program (DCP). Three new regional offices serving Africa and the Middle East were created within DCP: Middle East and North Africa, Eastern and Southern Africa, and West Africa. In 1989, the AME Program was reconstituted as a full program and continued to administer programs in the three regions in addition to a fourth, newly created Study Group on South Africa. The Africa and Middle East Programs files span in date from 1965-1976 and 1987-1994. The collection consists of the combined office files of AME program staff members Robert H. Edwards, Dr. John D. Gerhart, Steven M. Riskin, and Anna Wadia. File contents include correspondence, memoranda, meeting and conference minutes and agendas, reports, briefing papers, and information about various trips of Foundation Trustees to Africa. The bulk of the files are meeting and discussion group records from staff participation at internal Foundation meetings and external discussion groups facilitating collaboration with other philanthropies for common goals. One highlight is the rapporteur notes documenting the Foundation's 1989 Human Rights Meeting in Dakar, Senegal. The notes contain an overview of the Foundation's work to date in the field of Human Rights.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Organizational History
The Africa and Middle East (AME) Program originated in 1958 as the Near East and Africa Program, a regional program area within Overseas Development. It became part of the International Division in 1966 when the Overseas Development Program, along with other international Foundation programs became part of one International Division. A subsequent restructuring of the International Division occurred in 1980-1981 and led to the creation of the Developing Countries Program (DCP). Three new regional offices serving Africa and the Middle East were created within DCP: Middle East and North Africa, Eastern and Southern Africa, and West Africa. In 1989, the AME Program was reconstituted as a full program and continued to administer programs in the three regions in addition to a fourth, newly created Study Group on South Africa.
Biographical Note
Robert H. Edwards joined the Foundation as a Program Officer in 1966, and rose to be Head of the Middle East and Africa Program. He left the Foundation in 1977 to serve as President of Carleton College.
Dr. John D. Gerhart received his M.P.A. from Princeton in 1969 and began his career at Ford Foundation as an Economic Advisor to the Government of Botswana. Over the next thirty years, he held a variety of positions at the Foundation. From Program Advisor for Rural Development in Kenya, he moved to Cairo in 1980 to work as the Ford Foundation Representative for North Africa and the Middle East. In 1985, he was named Deputy Vice President for Developing Countries, a position that he held until 1989 when he became Director for Africa and the Middle East. He worked as the Foundation's representative in South Africa from 1989 to 1993. He died in July 2003.
Steven M. Riskin worked for the Ford Foundation for eight years between 1985 and 1992, initially as an Assistant Program Officer for AME Programs and then as Program Officer.
Anna Wadia succeeded Mr. Riskin as Program Officer in 1992 and served until 1994.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 4 series.
Scope and Contents
The Africa and Middle East Programs files span 1965-1976 and 1987-1994. The collection is comprised of the combined office files of Robert H. Edwards, Dr. John D. Gerhart, Steven M. Riskin, and Anna Wadia. The largest group of records is Series I: Meetings and Discussion Group Records. The files consist of meeting-related records, memoranda concerning grants and politics, and reports. These document staff participation in Foundation meetings and in discussion groups that brought together representatives from different philanthropies to discuss common goals. A highlight from this series are the Rapporteur Notes from a 1989 Dakar Human Rights Meeting which provide an overview of the Foundation's work in the field of Human Rights.
Series III. Reports, 1965-1990 (bulk 1989-1990)
This series includes a 1965 report on "Planning the Receipt of Aid" and a 1990 program strategy paper on "Planning for Democratic Governance and Public Policy in Eastern and Southern Africa."
Series IV. Trustee-Related Records, 1991-1992
This series documents visits by several Foundation trustees to Namibia, Nigeria, Senegal and Zimbabwe. The files hold correspondence, notes, travel agenda, briefing material, and biographical information about the trustees.
Separated Materials
Appendix A: Reports – Unpublished reports written by Ford Foundation staff and consultants were removed from their original folders, scanned and transferred to the Archives' collection of staff and consultant reports. See Appendix A for a list of these reports and their specific assigned number. The reports are listed in alphabetical order by author. The assigned number may be used to access reports in the online catalog.
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
- Meeting and Discussion Group Records, 1966-1976, 1987-1992; I
  Scope and Contents
  This series is comprised of correspondence, agenda, rapporteur notes and memoranda from Foundation staff who attended meetings and discussion groups. The records document internal Foundation meetings and working groups such as division conferences, as well as external meetings, conferences and working groups where Foundation staff met with representatives of other foundations or foreign governments. There also are files for the Donors in African Education working group and a file on the Ford Foundation's relations with the government of Sudan.
  - Law and Development Conference -- reports (separated) and outline of possible topics, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Society of International Law -- Panel on U.S. Law Schools and Developing Countries by Robert H. Edwards, 1968 February 15 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - International Legal Center -- Research and Training Committee (1 of 3), 1968-1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - International Legal Center -- Research and Training Committee (2 of 3), 1968-1975 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - International Legal Center -- Research and Training Committee (3 of 3), 1968-1975 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Committee on Women -- memoranda, reports, notes regarding the position of women at the Ford Foundation, 1971-1974 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - International Division Conference, September 1975 (1 of 2), 1975 September-December (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - International Division Conference, September 1975 (2 of 2), 1975 April-September (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Committee on Women -- memoranda and discussion papers on women's programming at the Ford Foundation, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - West Coast Trip -- Notes and Schedule, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Council on Foundations -- notes, correspondence and background for a meeting of the committee on international grantmaking, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - World Conference on Philanthropy, 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 1989 Dakar Human Rights Meeting -- Rapporteur Notes (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Program Review 1989 -- Rapporteur Notes, 1989 January (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Donors in African Education, 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Interview Skills Seminar, 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Sudan Government Relations, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Reproductive Health Meeting, 1990 June-December (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Sterling Forest/Tuxedo Governance Meeting, 1990 July-October (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - African Development Finance Conference, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Africa LEIG Meeting, 1990-1991 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Donors in African Education, 1991-1993 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - African Museums Meeting, 1991 March-August (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - MacArthur Foundation Meeting, 1991 March 4 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Council on Foundations, Chicago, Illinois, 1991 March-April (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Africa/Middle East Regional Program Review, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Reproductive Health Meeting, 1991 August 7 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Rural Poverty and Resources Meeting, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - African Rural Poverty Meeting, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Bellagio Conference, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Nelson Mandela Luncheon, 1991 October-December (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Harvard Center for International Affairs -- Political Liberalization in Africa, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - DAE Working Group on HE, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Africa Staff Meeting, 1991 December (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Worldwide International Affairs Program Meeting, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - South Africa, 1992 January-February (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - International Conference on Culture and Development, 1992 February-May (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Namibia/South Africa, 1992 April-August (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - John Gerhart Meeting Correspondence, 1992 May-November (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - South Africa Visit, 1992 September (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - South Africa Trip, 1992 October-December (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Memoranda, 1965-1994, bulk 1985-1994; II
  This series combines the files of three past program officers. Anna Wadia's memo files for 1992-1994 focus on grant proposals or grant-related meetings. Her files also contain correspondence between program staff. Robert Edward's files hold Foundation memoranda on the U.S. Balance of Payments (1965-1968), and Steven Riskin's files describe the political situation and repercussions for ordinary Sudanese during the civil war in Sudan (1985-1992) and South African television and newspaper ownership (1992-1994).
  - U.S. Balance of Payments, 1965-1968 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Sudan, 1985-1992 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Reflections on Foundation Programming Related to Disaster Preparedness and Response, 1989 February 10 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Higher Education in Africa, 1989-1993 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - 7th United Nations North American Regional NGO Symposium on the Question of Palestine, June 27-29, 1990, 1990 July 9 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - South Africa Media, 1992-1994 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Anna Wadia Memoranda File -- Meetings, Grant Updates (1 of 4), 1992 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Anna Wadia Memoranda File (2 of 4), 1993 January-July (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Anna Wadia Memoranda File (3 of 4), 1993 August-December (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Anna Wadia Memoranda File (4 of 4), 1994 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Reports, 1965, 1989-1990; III
  This series includes a 1965 report on "Planning the Receipt of Aid" and a 1990 program strategy paper on "Planning for Democratic Governance and Public Policy in Eastern and Southern Africa."
  - "Planning the Receipt of Aid" by O. S. Knowles, 1965 August (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - "Programming for Democratic Governance and Public Policy in Eastern and Southern Africa: A Program Strategy Paper", 1990 January 2 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Trustee-Related Records, 1991-1992; IV
  This series documents visits by several Foundation trustees to Namibia, Nigeria, Senegal and Zimbabwe. The files hold correspondence, notes, travel agenda, briefing material, and biographical information about the trustees.
  - Frances Fergusson Visit to Southern Africa, 1988-1992 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Senegal, 1991 August-October (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Preiskel/Ridings Africa Visit, 1991 September-November (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Nigeria, 1991 September-October (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Zimbabwe, 1991 September-October (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Namibia Visit, 1992 January-February (Box 4, Folder 18)